Sounds like you need a new chieftain.
Ha! There's an idea that's certain to win us friends.
Hmm, you said you were a hunter.
And I'll wager you're not an ordinary one.
It's not impossible, even for an outlander.
And Aratak couldn't refuse the challenge if you were known among the werak.
Wait, uh, me? Challenge Aratak?
I don't want to be chieftain of anything,
much less a bunch of Banuk that don't want me.
But you want to go to Thunder's Drum don't you?
You heard the spirit, she's suffering, tormented by the Daemon.
She longs to be free.
And perhaps when released from her bonds,
she can give you the answers you seek.
I can't believe I'm agreeing to this.
Fine!
BANUK: Look at what Ohlgrud did to this place.
BANUK: Hello.
BANUK: I have no interest in the frozen Tallneck.
Living machines are what's important to the hunt.
BANUK: Is there no end to the horrors the Daemon is willing to commit against us?
These will keep.
Cold, very cold, I get it!
Saving these for the trail.
Save these for the trail.
A fistful of bluegleam's worth braving the cold.
BANUK: The White Teeth have come to The Cut.
Not every day you see one of the great weraks.
BANUK: The longer you sit, the darker the colours end up being.
This really catches the eye.
BANUK: It's odd to see new machines in The Cut,
but we mustn't let them frighten us. We're Banuk.
ALOY: Is this what you…
KAMUT: Hush, hush!
A Shaman's secrets are not spoken aloud.
Is this what you wanted me to find?
Bind it to your spear, use it to attach this for now.
You'll find more, I'm sure.
Why are you helping me?
The blue light is fading, the machine songs are ending, and…
And what does the Conclave do?
The sit, they chant, they observe.
No more! We must fight for it.
And you? You are a fighter, we share a cause.
I'm not sure we do.
I'm not even sure what the cause is, but I'm grateful.
No need for thanks, only action.
Now I can attach modification parts to my spear.
Works for me. Might as well get started improving my spear.
BANUK: I've heard of your performance at the hunting grounds.
BANUK: Everyone gets lucky occasionally.
BANUK: The Daemon at Thunder's Drum…
Ah, there she is!
There's my other set of hands.
How's your metal cooling, hmm?
My, uh, metal is cooling pretty well Gildun, and yours?
Ah, you know, nothing comes out of the forge perfect.
Come, sit, I've got an old delving story that'll turn that red hair white.
Hold that thought, Gildun. Another time, okay?
Anytime you like.
SHAMAN: We remember Banukai.
SHAMAN: When the Old Ones were fresh in their graves and our numbers were still small, it was she who led us through the frozen wastes.
We also remember the Ravenous Tribe who delighted in sucking the marrow from our broken bones.
Everywhere Banukai and her werak fled, the Ravenous Tribe were never far behind.
Seeking a way to defeat them, Banukai went into the wastes and let the wind whip her cheeks.
And when the cold brought sleep she dreamt of light.
She saw it behind the world, a great calming sheet of icy blue.
And she saw something new.
Herds of machines each filled with the same blue light.
When she woke, she knew which star to follow.
She walked for many days and nights until she arrived at a temple built from sparkling ice.
At the gates of the temple she was met by the machines from her dream.
Who bowed to her as she entered.
Inside Banukai discovered the blue light bubbling from a hole in the snowy earth like a spring.
"You bid me come," she said.
"My people need aid. Will you provide it?"
The machines whispered to Banukai,
"we go where the light goes for we are its chosen vessels."
"There is darkness in your heart, it cannot hold the light for long."
"Carry it to your people if you must, but the cost will be great."
Banukai waded into the pool.
The light reared like a nest of snakes and struck Banukai, piercing her skin,
filling her up.
Banukai did not scream, though she was in agony.
Banukai did not collapse, though her limbs shook.
She climbed from the pool and carried the light inside her.
She marched toward home and the machines marched behind her.
As she walked, the light struggled to push its way out of her,
but the machines were there to aid her.
She sewed her body shut with their cables, patched herself with their metal,
and kept the light within.
When she arrived the forces of the Ravenous Tribe had surrounded the camp.
Although the light had left her with a thousand wounds, Banukai charged.
And because she held the light, the machines followed.
The Ravenous Tribe killed many, but those in camp rushed to join the battle.
They gathered pieces of the fallen machines and from them fashioned weapons.
And it was with these that Banukai's people repaid the suffering the Ravenous Tribe had brought upon them.
When quiet descended, Banukai finally fell.
The machines bowed their heads and the werak wept.
The light she'd held within her drifted from her wounds and rose to the sky.
And for just a moment, before life left her, Banukai knew the truth of the blue light.
And she felt peace.
We remember Banukai.
The first to crawl from the cave beneath the world, who brought the machines to us.
When we speak the name of our tribe we remember her.
And we will not forget.
SHAMAN: We remember Banukai.
SHAMAN: When the Old Ones were fresh in their graves and our numbers were still small, it was she…
SEKULI: What does the Outlander want?
ALOY: I'm looking for Sekuli.
SEKULI: You found her. Come, come, let's get it over with.
ALOY: Is this swaying or is it just me?
SEKULI: The wood bends with the wind.
Quite a view you've got up here.
It's a useful perspective.
How fleeting we are in the world is so wide.
From up here you can see how the light paints across the land, ever changing.
That's a lesson: all our marks will pass.
That outlook sounds a little depressing for a painter.
Haven't met many artists, have you?
The Banuk rock paintings are impressive, but, um…
You want to know what they mean.
That's not the right question, but I'll answer anyway.
Some are a call to the machines, the sacred shapes you see on metal casings or on a Cauldron door.
Do the machines listen to the call?
I don't know.
Others like mine are a call to the tribe.
You could say inspiration or prophecy.
And sometimes even men listen if the painting is loud enough.
Have you always been a painter?
I've always painted, but I wasn't a painter until I was driven out of Ban-Ur.
Up there the markings are eternal.
They paint over the same lines, the same colours, over and over.
As a child, I learned from copying them.
As I grew, my heart sank at the familiarity.
Song's Edge needs new stories.
I scrubbed its past off this rock to start anew, but a new start needs new colours.
Fresh pigments like none have seen.
Ourea said you two were friends.
I paint about what I feel now, not the way things used to be.
Ourea understood, most Banuk didn't.
I would have been exiled if she hadn't had Aratak take me into their werak.
These pigments you want, where should I look for them?
Salts gather at the edges of geysers and hot pools,
crystals cling to the rocks and cliffs.
I'll see what I can find for you.
Seek out the vibrant ones, a spring of sudden colour among snow or rock or metal.
That's its own reward. But I'd reward you as well.
These are perfect, and like all perfect things.
they must be watered down or ground into a paste.
Way of the world.
I'll see you again.
If you do find any pigments out there, don't put them on your tongue.
I'm not even going to ask.
I'll bet my name's all over Song's Edge.
Might be time to challenge Aratak.
My people have been telling tales of your accomplishments.
Seems you have taken a special interest in our stretch of snow, outlander.
Yes, and apparently this is the only way I'll get to see all of it.
Is this a challenge?
For the werak.
You? Ha! This must be a joke!
It is not a joke Aratak!
Now I see. The outlander's your pawn.
And with you backing her claim I have no choice but to accept.
I expected better of you, sister.
It was you who forbid me from Thunder's Drum, brother.
Brother and sister?
This is a little more complicated than I thought.
No, it's simple.
You will meet me at the Frostfigures and I'll put a quick end to this mockery.
I suppose I owe you an explanation.
Yeah, I suppose you do.
So why didn't you tell me that you and Aratak are siblings?
I thought I wouldn't have to.
I'm surprised Aratak brought it up in front of a stranger.
He must be very angry.
I'm not always best judge of…
People?
I prefer the company of spirits.
Or simply my own.
I didn't want you to think of our pilgrimage of some sort of family squabble.
It's much more important than that.
It's bold, I'll give you that, going after your own brother.
He gave me no choice.
He thinks I'm a child to be shoved to the back of the hunt.
He would forbid me from my destiny.
And yet part of me did it knowing he would forgive me, eventually.
He always does.
Family drama aside, what's this challenge meant to be anyway?
You and Aratak will hunt machines at the Frostfigures.
The victor will be the fastest.
It won't be easy.
Nothing about this has been so far.
When you meet us at the starting point, I'll tell you more.
It will be simpler to explain from the base of the hills.
Ourea, it's not about who's related to who.
I want to know what's inside Thunder's Drum.
The spirit, the Daemon, and how it all connects the machines.
But if we're gonna go through with this, I need you to be straight with me.
I … underestimated you.
And Aratak.
I won't make that mistake again.
See you at the Frostfigures then.
So, off to risk my life in order to take charge of a Banuk hunting band.
Just what I always wanted.
Frostfigures here I come.
BANUK: These new machines, another horror visited upon us by the Daemon.
BANUK: No reason to leave The Cut,
the weather only gets hotter as you venture south.
OK, the Frostfigures should be just up there.
The Frostfigures. Aratak and Ourea must be close.
Outlander!
I have prevailed over such challenges before and fear none.
But this one is foolish.
You're not Banuk.
You do not understand my responsibilities.
I ask you, one hunter to another, withdraw.
Will you let us go to Thunder's Drum?
You haven't seen what's up there, outlander.
I will not risk my sister's life again.
Then we'd better get on with this.
So be it!
I will bury your insolent claim in the frozen ground!
Enough! Let us begin.
To hunt, to strive, that is the way of the Banuk and of the contest before you.
You will climb the Frostfigures from the east, Aratak from the west.
Each trail wends its way through deadly machines.
Hunters from the werak will be posted along the way.
They will hail you, calling out machines for you to slay.
Your hunt will take you around the ridge to the centre,
where you must descend to the valley for your final kill.
Each time after your prey has fallen, you must launch a beacon such as this so that all our kin will see your progress.
Kill machines, launch balloons. Got it.
So, the first of us to launch third balloon wins?
Well, yes.
And as challenger your path to victory is harder.
If even one of your beacons comes in after Aratak's, he prevails.
[laughs] You had your chance, outlander.
So did you.
The hunt begins on my mark.
Now!
All right, gotta head up that mountain.
Looks like there are a few ways to go up, and those rock paintings mark the path.
Okay, up we go.
I seem to be on the right path.
C'mon Aloy, time is wasting.
Almost to the top.
BANUK: Alright challenger, you need to take out the herd below, every machine.
Kill a herd, okay, I can do that.
BANUK: I've dropped a ladder for you! Climb on up and launch your marker!
Alright, here we go.
BANUK: Now climb the ridge and launch your balloon.
Aratak knows what he's doing. No time to waste.
BANUK: Take the rappel point to the next challenge.
BANUK: Two Bellowbacks ahead challenger.
BANUK: Kill them both, none of the other machines matter.
Alright, two dead Bellowbacks coming up!
Right on target!
BANUK: Here challenger, raise your marker!
Now where's that balloon?
BANUK: Come on over here and launch your balloon!
I'm ahead, but only by a little. I gotta get moving.
BANUK: Now take the zip line and work your way down to the valley.
Storm's kicking up. Can't see much.
Close now.
Almost down.
Alright, to the last challenge.
Something's wrong.
My kin should be here, driving in our final quarry.
They're right behind us!
That's it, I'm already gone.
I think I'm in the clear.
Makes this a little easier.
So it's true.
Frostclaws from Thunder's Drum.
The attack cut short the competition.
Naturally, there can be no result. It is void.
You saw what she did!
She defeated the machines, not I.
It is proven, she is the better hunter.
We are Banuk. Survive, prevail, what else matters?
My blood is in your teeth.
I take my place behind you on the hunt.
No more hunters may make the ascent to Thunder's Drum.
The way is closed to all but the chieftain and myself.
It is not my place, but I would ask a boon.
To accompany you, and my sister.
It might be permitted, but only if you do as I say.
No.
Only if you do as I say.
Thunder's Drum awaits.
There's a camp at its base, Longnotch it's called.
Meet us there when you're ready… chieftain.
A new outfit and a weapon like Aratak's.
I guess the chieftain gets the Chieftain's gear.
And now to Longnotch. Nothing to keep me from Thunder's Drum.
Think of summer sun, breeze through the trees.